sewing.
Heat
up
[music]
Carol, welcome to the signal room. I'm
so excited to have you here.
We're in a really exciting but little
scary time with artificial intelligence.
I recall back in the early 90s how
excited everyone was when we all of a
sudden started to have this internet
thing and now I don't know what it would
be like without it. Even since then we
now have cell phone technology and now
AI is this whole other
universe that seems to have like
limitless potential but at the same time
there's a lot to be concerned about. I
think
yes,
my initial conversation with you, I
started to understand a little bit about
what you do. And Assad, there's a real
need for people like you to keep us
grounded, making sure we're doing things
that keep us human and not losing sight
of what human beings need. Maybe you
could tell us a little about your
company, Equal Access Language Services.
It has a lot of implications just in the
name, which I think is wonderful. Maybe
you could tell us about the
organization, what you do, and what
inspired you to start the company.
Thank you, Chris. Since it was infused
in our interaction, we've always been
worried about, right,
oh my god, are we humans going to be
replaced by technology? That happens
also in the language industry when we
thought that maybe translators were
going to be replaced by machine
translation and it's been around for
decades yet it hasn't replaced human
translators. What it has done is that it
has enhanced all those capabilities. My
company Equal Access Language Services
is about eliminating
language based discrimination
and to help people understand that AI
will never replace ethics, care, empathy
or reward. But we definitely want AI to
be a part of our evolution and enhance
access. My company does provide language
access training to health care
providers. We want to make sure that
everybody from the front desk person to
management to leadership understand the
impact of language in healthcare. I
educate professionals in this. That's
the part that makes my company very
different from other language services
providers. In addition to that, we offer
language services like interpretation
translation. It's interesting when it
think about access there's so many
different facets to it. That's the stuff
that's really being discussed for the
most part um at least across the US. I'm
suspect it's similar in other places
because there's definitely shortages of
nursing, shortages in clinical care for
some specialties and increasingly more
need for general practitioners. Capacity
is obviously a challenge but we're also
in a global community. The world is not
as big as we once felt like it was.
There's a lot of need almost in any
place you go for a really diverse array
of services, making sure that it's
accessible from a language standpoint,
not only the cultural things that drive
people's decision-m about their care,
but the simplest of things, just being
able to communicate and understand
another human being. It's something I
don't think gets enough attention. So,
I'm really excited about what you're
doing. Uh this conversation is one I've
been really looking forward to. We're
talking about things that are core and
basic that human beings need. We cannot
lose sight of the core needs of a human
being. The very first thing is can I
understand what somebody's saying to me?
Can they understand me? It it's really
core and it's got to be front and center
in anything we're doing from a
development standpoint.
Let's talk about the transformation
we're entering into. I think about it in
terms of workforce readiness. Trust is
probably one of the bigger factors. I'd
love to get your take on how do you
really address the trust factor. We're
at a point in time when trust has eroded
over the last couple of decades. From
your standpoint, what are some of the
core things we need to make sure that
our clinicians, our nurses, our medical
assistants, our frontline staff are
interacting with patients? What are some
of the core things they really need to
have and that we need to be thinking
about helping them to be proficient to
meet the challenge?
I talk about a communication equity,
right? Because I think every provider
must develop those core skills that you
talk about, right? And specifically in
my case, I talk about language access
skills. And this includes language
awareness, interpreter ethics, knowing
when and how to use professional
language services, for example, because
in reality, if you think about
communication, that's the most important
and powerful diagnostic tool. So when we
think about that, let's let that sink in
for a minute. Communication is the most
important diagnostic tool. So when there
are threats to that, if that tool is
compromised by language barriers, every
other aspect of care will fail or be
compromised from diagnosis to discharge.
So everything will become less effective
and also more expensive. And I think
this is where we make mistakes because
we associate language access services
with an administrative thing almost a
burden. But what I want to say is that
they are absolutely key for patients
safety. There are tons of studies
demonstrating that language barriers
impact beyond what we think about. For
example, there is less compliance from
the patient perspective when there are
communication errors, right? If there is
no language accessibility, they are less
likely to comply with what the doctor
said. And this will influence the trust
in the doctor. I want people to think
about the rapport they create with the
patient. How important that is and how
interaction is a foundation for healing.
That's what language access is coming to
provide enhancement to your relationship
with the limited English proficient
population which is a huge portion of
our US population. about 26 million
people in the US don't speak English and
all of them every single one of them
will have medical encounter at some
point in their lives. So we have to
think about effective communication and
inclusion through language access.
Discuss more about it.
When we think about some of the recent
changes in legislation, we've talked
about the recent executive order
intended to officially say English is
the language in the United States.
There's some debate around how far that
should go. Legislation doesn't
necessarily change human behavior and it
doesn't affect what human beings need.
Talk to us about your perspective as
someone trying to improve access and
understands that language is at the core
of of what's going to help people have
access and get to that trusted
relationship with their physician. They
can't understand how do they even get
started and have a relationship.
You mentioned several things. One is the
access part, right? I use the comparison
between language access with a ramp and
I make the distinction between ramp and
staircase. So you mentioned the changes
in policy, right? When we are told the
official language of the US is English,
there is nothing essentially wrong with
that. It's like saying staircases are
not wrong, but if you have a wheelchair,
that's right. then you have an issue
with just the st their cases. It's the
same way if we say the official language
of the US is English and in addition to
that they repeal the new executive order
that talked about meaningful access and
language access for those who have
language barriers then it becomes a real
problem. Right? I use that comparison
because it makes inequity visible. Like
when we compare a ramp with a staircase,
if we replace wheelchair ramps with
stairs, everyone will recognize that as
discrimination. Yet, when we make
English the only language of care, we
don't see the same thing. When a patient
walks into a hospital and can't
understand the forms, the consent
process, or the discharge instructions,
they're not being given the same access
to care as others, right? is like asking
them to climb invisible stairs. For
those 26 million people in the US who
are limited English proficient that is a
very steep staircase is exhausting and
sometimes it will threat threaten their
lives.
I want that to be very clear. Another
interesting thing that happened to me
when I read the executive order 14224
which is the one that talks about
English as the official language. um
realized how executive orders are
useless when it comes to protect civil
rights. Even one signature
though that the civil right of language
accessibility which is a civil right
protected under title six in jeopardy.
It made me think that civil rights need
to be protected by actual laws. Just
like the Americans with Disabilities Act
is protected is passed through Congress.
We should be able to protect
communication in general. Whether you
are a deaf, deb blind or heart of
hearing person or if you don't speak
English, you should be protected the
same way
and we are not. So I think that
we need to emphasize the importance of
changing policies at that level. That's
an excellent point and civil rights.
Oftentimes we don't necessarily think
about some of the more
foundational aspects of what it's like
to be a human being. When it comes to
how we are providing care, when you talk
about health care, we're forgetting the
most core thing and it's right in the
term health care. We can't claim to care
and take care of people if we don't
first try to understand them and start
to get an understanding of what they
need.
AI is not going to protect your dignity.
human will is nothing against AI. Where
do the capabilities of AI start and end
and when do the human capabilities are
better utilized? Like when do you really
need a human brain to provide the
one of the things that we've got to
figure out is where does AI work? We
know there's a fear out there. Is AI
going to take my job? It's a challenge
for people who do translation and
interpretation for a living. They have
concerns about that. talk about you
where you see the risks and what should
we be looking at in terms of guiding
principles to help us make sure that
we're using it as a tool to enhance and
and empower people to operate at the
highest level their lensure as opposed
to just rip and replace. We obviously
cannot replace human beings with
machinery or technology.
Yeah. Addressing your question at the
beginning, you said that many people in
the language services industry are
afraid because AI represents a big
threat and I agree that there is a sense
of doom in the language services side
except we have come to realize that only
those that don't know how to use AI
probably will be left without a job. But
I will go even further and say that this
is the precise moment when we need to
emphasize ethics and ethical behavior
not only from interpreters.
[clears throat] I teach ethics to
interpreters. My colleagues were very
worried about the perfect word and the
exact word. And that's actually the
thing that AI might replace is you if
you don't know about a word, you have
your phone and you know exactly where to
look for the perfect word. But it's your
brain and your heart and your cultural
norms that are going to give you the
ethics aspect, right? It's not AI. You
can't outsource ethics to AI. And this
is why I emphasize on that not only for
interpreters, for physicians as well,
for nurses, for social workers. I
actually became very familiar with every
single one of the codes of ethics to
incorporate them in the training.
Effective inclusion through language
access is a training for healthcare
professionals that underscores the
mandate they have nurses, social
workers, doctors, medic medical doctors,
pharmacists,
right?
Dentists and also lawyers. Right? I read
all of these six holes of ethics and
they all have a mandate on communication
and effective communication with the
community that they serve. We have
already hinted at the fact that
effective communication could be a
combination between AI and humans,
right? Ethical communication. And you
can't offer effective communication to
your community unless you include as
part of your community all of those who
don't speak the language. the 9% of the
population in the United States. That
framework
of language access as a civil right is
what is going to help you as a
professional really deliver safe care.
We have some ideas around what AI
shouldn't do.
From your perspective, how do you see AI
really being useful? You mentioned a
really important point. AI isn't going
to replace people.
but it might replace roles where people
are not learning how to employ and use
AI to help them in the work that they
do. So what are some of the things that
you think it could be useful for people
that are currently doing interpretation
and translation?
Yes. So AI is already very useful
because it's going to expand access.
It's going to make it faster where we
can produce a translation of thousands
of words very quickly. But you still
need to review that translation.
Companies that combine AI with human in
the loop approaches are going to excel.
In my opinion, AI is going to make
things faster. Not necessarily accurate.
This is when humans come, right? And
when but when you combine the two, then
you can offer faster services, broader
range of languages perhaps, broader
range of services as well. But always
keeping the human perspective. For
example, I educate my own clients. I
talk to them about AI, how that will
reduce the cost of translation because I
will use post editing. The human is
going to compare the translation and it
has been proven to be useful. To give
you a recent example, the word safety in
English and my client had the word safe
and then slash the T. The use of that
acronym in English makes perfect sense.
We translated it using AI. The AI
translated it literally and it made no
sense. So T for safety or I'm sorry T
for turning into action for example. It
wouldn't translate the same. You need a
human to find the most creative solution
in that particular point. Still, we the
translation with AI, but we used the
human for the post editing to make sure
that the client was actually conveying
to the Spanish speaking audience the
same thing, not something that sounded
like a machine. And that's important.
I'm giving you one example of how we can
use the AI
and still use humans in the loop, which
is what I advocate for safety. This is
very important specifically in
healthcare. Humans provide that safety
point and compliance.
I think it's important and one of the
things I've been wrestling with myself
as a data person is how do I help
organizations identify places where we
can use it. There's going to be a lot of
attention from a legal and compliance
standpoint, risk management. Thank God
for people who are trained and
proficient in those areas. They're going
to help to keep us from missteps.
But at the same time, we don't want to
be paralyzed because we're afraid we're
going to do the wrong thing. We have to
find ways that we can actually deploy it
where it can enhance safety. We want to
be looking for those kind of
opportunities.
Yes. Really emphasizing that artificial
intelligence is not moral intelligence.
As far as I understand, artificial
intelligence doesn't have a conscious
yet, but humans do. So, I believe in a
partnership with AI, not in a
replacement of humans. On that note, I
think it's very important to emphasize
that we as humans have to continue to
see the ethical aspect of care always
and also think of the type of standards
that
we would apply to ourselves. For
example, many people in the AI front
think that all translations are going to
be replaced by AI. And I always ask them
and I have had at least six informal
interviews with tech people or medical
tech people and I asked them if you are
in a country where nobody speaks your
language and you get sick and you go to
the doctor would you feel okay if
somebody comes with a tablet telling you
your diagnosis, prognosis and treatment
and that all has been translated by a
machine and you only see the tablet.
Would that still okay with you? And the
six person told me actually no I would
prefer a doctor to tell me right
so even with an interpreter so I'm
saying okay if that is the standard you
want for yourself what makes you think
that the other person is going to want a
lesser standard
I remember the first time I called a
support line for a computer I was having
difficulty with and I got a machine on
the other end u it was very frustrating.
The models were looking at decision
trees where my answer would trigger one
of two options and go through a
sequence. It was trying to guide me
through what it thought I wanted to have
to talk about. And there was really a
very it's almost impossible to get it to
skip over things to get to where you
wanted to critical thing we need to
understand is in healthcare. It's much
more important than when you're just
calling to get support for your
computer. How a person communicates and
what they need in that moment is even
more intense than necessary than the
support comp.
In healthcare is really a matter of life
and death. There are examples of how the
limited English proficient population
experience four times more errors that
could change their health and their
life. Like they are going severe
temporary errors. The agency for
healthcare research and quality
published a study in 2012 that talked
exactly about this. Limited English
proficient are four times more likely to
experience severe temporary harm than
English speakers. If that doesn't show
you the importance of the language
barrier,
nothing else will right in in healthcare
is particularly important. There are
several studies that I quote all the
time in my trainings about why language
accessibility is not just a nice thing
to have. It's a safety task. And I think
that we need to have that perspective
before we even implement anything in
healthcare. What I find in my
work is that perspective is still fuzzy.
We still see healthcare providers
solving language barriers with in in any
which way using children and train
interpreters. I recently saw an attorney
but I'm telling you three weeks ago I
saw an attorney who wanted to discuss
the terms of a plea deal with her
client. Just imagine if that was your
case. You're I don't know some country
that's not necessarily friendly and or
forget the friendliness, but you don't
speak parsy and you make a mistake. You
are not even aware that culturally you
couldn't make that mistake. You're now
in court and somebody's trying to tell
you what you are about to face with
Google Translate. Would that make you
feel like, oh yeah, okay, I can go with
this. No, you probably are going to be
like, can someone explain to me?
We're coming up on time, but I I want to
touch on something. There's been a lot
of conversation and different
perspectives on what we were calling
diversity, equity, and inclusion. You've
talked about inclusion is
infrastructure. I think that's a really
important thing for us to be thinking
about as we're designing. What do you
think it means to design language access
into systems rather than adding it
later? This is something that we've got
to build in from the very foundation.
Talk to me a little bit about what that
looks like from your perspective. How do
we make sure that's where we take this
as we're developing?
Yes, I think that's such an important
point you make, Chris, about changing
something into an infrastructure, not
just a nice to have. Diversity, equity,
and inclusion. It's a good example
because we really haven't come up with
many ways to measure success in that
front other than numbers of people of
this race or that race or this gender.
that in terms of outcomes, I think we
are lacking when we include language
access, we can measure healthcare
outcomes between people that had medical
encounters with professional
interpreters versus people that had a
medical encounter with no interpreter or
with an ad hoc interpreter. The
literature is there. The ones that made
few much fewer mistakes were the
professional interpreters. That is what
I mean by turning this into an
infrastructure. Language access has to
be part of your planning, your strategic
planning. It has to be aligned from the
beginning.
Not just as an afterthought. There is
always no budget for language access. In
some major hospitals, there is and has
been for a very long time, but some
institutions think that because they are
smaller or because they are nonprofit,
they have an excuse to not have a plan
for language access. Great. We don't
have an excuse. Just the same way as we
have to provide ramps for people with
wheelchairs, we have to incorporate
language access. So that's what I mean
by making it part of the system. When
you think about communication harm, it
causes the same kind of harm as
medication errors or surgical mistakes,
right? Sometimes it's even worse because
they sometimes go unnotice. And I think
this is part of the problem of language
access. We need to make them visible. To
give you an example, when I worked for a
hos in one of the major hospitals in the
US, which was it's a it honor to me to
hampboard there, but I remember having
the conversation with my manager about
moving language a language access our
department language access services
under patient safety because that
hospital actually had a complete
department of patient safety and it was
under an administrative side and I'm
like this is a clinical issue is not
only administrative. So anyway, I
created a video called saving lives in
many language. There was a contest on
patient safety and I would like to share
that video if you allow me. Not now, but
I can share the link. It talked about
right
how language access was a matter of
patient safety and I made several
examples there. That video went on to
win first prize in the contest. I'm very
proud of that. But besides being proud,
I think this is an example of having
that infrastructure. We have to have it
just as you budget for anything else,
including ramps and access access points
when you're building a hospital
physically. You have to have the
language access awareness. And
well, I'm excited to see the video and I
think we can put it in the notes to push
along with the show as well because I'm
sure folks would enjoy seeing that. I'll
share that you and I created a course
that's effective inclusion through
language access. The course walks you
through how to implement language access
effectively and it also talks about the
interaction between language access and
AI. I have seven modules that talk about
that and I think it's the perfect
opportunity for healthcare providers to
take this kind of course. It helps with
compliance with the affordable care act
section 1557 that talks about training
on language access. This is great that
we still have the affordable care act
plan section 1557 that secures that
training by creating that training is
the first of its kind and is the most
comprehensive one. That's what I wanted
to emphasize.
If you could tell our listeners one one
structural change for equitable
communication tomorrow, what would that
change be? And if you're running an
organization that's having to drive
through this transformation, what would
you tell people they need to be thinking
about from your perspective?
I would tell people that inclusion isn't
a soft skill. It's infrastructure.
Language access is the bridge between
compliance and compassion.
And whether through human interpreters
or AI, we're not just translating words,
we're translating humanity to keep in
mind. humanity such a concept that we
don't think about it like we should
these days. All this emphasis on
technology and AI we're still talking
about people here and it's really
important to keep the focus where it
belongs it is on about human beings and
human relationship.
So as we wrap if folks want to learn
more about what you do in your
organization they realize they need some
help in this area how would they get in
touch with you? Thank you, Chris. They
can email me carolve
valiaqualacislanguageservices.com
and that's the best way to communicate
with me. I also have a podcast called
Language Access Matters and the main
purpose is to teach people about what
language is all about. It's been on air
for two years and I encourage everybody
to listen because it's going to change
our culture with regards to language
access. That's my hope that we promote
change from our heart and our thinking.
My main goal to create that course was
to change minds around language access
and and create a more compassionate care
for limited English proficient persons.
Ultimately, Chris, you mentioned travel
at the beginning of our conversation
today and how we have a smaller village
than before. It's going to affect
language is going to affect all of us.
If you set foot outside of your country
to a country you want to visit and you
don't speak the local language, you're
going to realize how important it is
that we all think
about language accessibility because
it's going to benefit you. I can tell
you countless stories of people that I
met in Spain or in Kata where I am right
now that tell me, "Oh my god, I did have
this language barrier and I felt this
way and that other way." So I love that
people
step out of their own shoes to taste how
it is to experience. [laughter]
Carol, I can't thank you enough for
being with me today. Really excited to
continue to follow the work that you're
doing. I think it's incredibly important
and in my own work. I intend to stay
close and make sure that
run things by you when it comes to
healthcare. So, thank you so much for
being with us. I am really looking
forward to the next time. I know we're
going to have opportunities to have more
conversations around this because I
think it's really important as AI is
evolving, there seems to be a gap in
terms of the technology and really that
making sure that it's leaning in to
improve access and it really takes into
account not only the geographic,
cultural and religious aspects that make
people unique, but the core stuff is
really language and communication. Very
excited to continue to work with you.
Thank you so much for joining me here.
Thank you, Grace. I just want to
emphasize that you're doing exactly what
anybody in tech should do, which is
worry about the human aspect that should
not be forgotten or outsourced to tech.
It is a privilege to be with you, share
space, and combine our ways of thinking
coming from two different approaches
into something that probably going to
enhance healthcare.
Thank you for inviting.
That's it for this episode of the Signal
Room. If today's conversation sparks
something in you, an idea, a challenge,
or perspective worth amplifying, I'd
love to hear from you. Message me on
LinkedIn or visit sigaroompodcast.com
to explore being a guest on an upcoming
episode. Until next time, stay tuned,
stay curious, and stay human.